Lewis, Frederick Thomas, 1875-1951. Papers, 1663-1951: A Finding Aid.
Papers, 1663, 1711-1951.
Francis A.Countway Library of Medicine. Center for the History of Medicine.
Lewis, Frederic Thomas, 1875-1951.
1.7 cubic ft. in 1 record carton, 1 document box, 1 half document box, 1 half legal document box.
The Frederic Thomas Lewis Papers, 1663, 1711-1951, document the research, teaching, and professional activities of Frederic Thomas Lewis, James Stillman Professor of Comparative Anatomy at Harvard Medical School.
The Frederic Thomas Lewis Papers were acquired by the Harvard Medical Library in the Francis A. Countway Library of Medicine.
Access requires advance notice. Consult the Public Services Librarian for further information.
Index Terms
Eliot, Charles William, 1834-1926.; Ernst, Harold C. (Harold Clarence) 1856-1922.; Lewis, Frederick Thomas, 1875-1951.; Minot, George Richards, 1885-1950.; Minot, Charles Sedgwick, 1852-1914.; Boston Medical Library.; Harvard Medical School. Dept. of Anatomy.; Harvard Medical School--Study and teaching.; Embryology.; Embryologists.; Medical education.; Microscopes.
Series Arrangement
Series I. Personal and Professional Correspondence, 1902-1952
Subseries A. Harvard Medical School Administrative Correspondence, 1902-1952
Subseries B. Charles S. Minot Portrait Correspondence, 1938-1943
Series II. Teaching Records, 1908-1945
Series III. Administrative Activities Records, 1914-1940
Series IV. Research Correspondence and Notes, 1663, 1711-1951
Subseries A. History of Medicine Research Records, 1663, 1711-1951
Subseries B. Microscope Research Records, 1921-1950
Subseries C. Exhibit Notes, 1932-1940
Biography
Frederic Thomas Lewis (FTL) was James Stillman Professor of Comparative Anatomy at Harvard Medical School where his research focused on embryology, the development of veins and blood vessels, and the history of the development of the microscope. The son of Charles Sanford Lewis and Nettie Farnum (Brown) Lewis, he was born in Cambridge, Mass. on 18 March 1875. FTL entered Harvard College in 1893 and, having completed the required courses for a bachelor’s degree, spent his fourth year at Harvard College in advanced courses in biology. He was awarded a Bachelor of Arts degree in 1897 with special honors in natural history and, based on the advanced courses he had completed in biology, was awarded a Master of Arts degree in 1898. He entered Harvard Medical School (HMS) in 1897 and received the MD in 1901. He married Ethel May Stickney on 30 July 1904, and they had one child.
Following graduation FTL returned to HMS as Austin Teaching Fellow in Embryology in 1901. He remained at HMS, becoming an Instructor in Histology 1902-1906, Assistant Professor of Embryology 1915-1931, and James Stillman Professor of Comparative Anatomy 1931-1941. In 1941 he retired as Emeritus.
During his first two decades at HMS, FTL’s research in embryology focused on the development of veins and lymphatic vessels. In later years he investigated the shapes and patterns of epithelial cells, concluding that physical factors and geometrical principle governed the arrangement of such polyhedral bodies. He contributed chapters regarding the development of the digestive system for a volume entitled Human Embryology edited by Keibel and Mall in 1910. He became the author of a widely used textbook, Histology (based on Stohr’s Histologie), first published in 1906.
During his years at HMS, FTL became an authority on the history and development of the microscope; he researched, cataloged, and expanded the collection of microscopes left to HMS by Professor Harold C. Ernst. He collected many books, pamphlets, letters, and artifacts pertaining to the history of medicine and mounted exhibits on anatomy, embryology, and histology in the corridors of the Department of Anatomy.
FTL also maintained active memberships in a number of professional organizations, acting as editor of The American Naturalist 1907-1908, and associate editor of The Anatomical Record 1908-1921. While a member of the American Association of Anatomists he served on the executive committee 1909-1913, as vice-president 1914-1916, and as president 1936-1938. He was a Fellow of the American Association for the Advancement of Science, the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, and the Royal Microscope Society. He was both a councillor 1913-1926 and vice-president 1926-1929 of the Boston Society of Natural History. FTL died at his home in Waban, Massachusetts on 2 June 1951, at the age of 76.
Scope and Content Note
The Frederic Thomas Lewis Papers, 1663, 1711-1951, are the result of Lewis's administrative, teaching, and research activities at HMS faculty member. Records include notes, correspondence, catalogs, course exams, and photographs from his research on both the history of medicine and the microscope, as well as his administrative and teaching activities at HMS. The FTL Papers also includes FTL's 17th and 18th century letters and notes collected for his study and exhibits of the history of medicine; these items appear in Series IV.
Eleven folders of photographs and photographic prints listed in the collection are housed in box 3. Oversize items are housed in box 4 and in one oversize folder is housed separately.
Related Materials
Related collections in the Center for the History of Medicine include:
Frederic Thomas Lewis's faculty publications (1.Mh.1902.L)
Charles Sedgwick Minot Papers (H MS c21; GA 54.10)
Geroge Richards Minot Papers (GA 55)
For more information on related materials, consult the Public Services Librarian.
Box and Folder List
- I. Personal and Professional Correspondence, 1902-1952
  Series I includes FTL's personal and professional correspondence from his teaching and administrative activities at HMS. Included in Subseries B is correspondence from FTL's efforts to raise funds for a portrait of Charles S. Minot at HMS.
  Photographs listed in Series I are housed in box 3. Oversized materials listed in Series I are housed in an oversized folder.
  - A. Harvard Medical School Administrative Correspondence, 1902-1952
    Subseries A includes colleague correspondence from FTL's activities as an HMS faculty member, as well as from his collecting historical items for HMS, including the Oliver Wendell Holmes Loving Cup and a portrait of Edward Bromfield, an early pioneer in the use of microscopes, which later hung at HMS.
    Interfiled alphabetically by topic or correspondent. Photographs listed in Subseries A are housed in box 3.
    - (Box 1)
    - Bremer, John Lewis, 1927, 1.
    - Briggs, L. B., 1909, 2.
    - Bromfield (Edward) Exhibit, 1927-1949, 3.
    - Bromfield Portrait, 1932-1949, 4.
    - Cohen, Bernard I., 1948-1949, 5.
    - Cushing, Harvey, 1916-1947, 6-7.
    - Eliot, Charles W., 1908-1916, 8.
    - Greene, Jerome D., 1941, 9.
    - Hanus, Paul H., 1909, 10.
    - Hergoz, Maximillian, 1914, 11.
    - Holmes Loving Cup, 1940, 12.
    - Holmes Loving Cup, 1940, photograph ((box 3, folder 6))
    - Kampmeier, Otto, 1950-1951, 13.
    - Keibel, Franz, 1921-1929, n.d., 14.
    - Lowell, Lawrence A., 1910-1943, 15.
    - Mass. State Medical Board, 1915-1919, 16.
    - Minot, Charles S., 1902-1937, 17-18.
    - Minot, George R., 1931-1942, 19.
    - Minot, Lucy, 1914-1935, 20.
    - Moore, Edward C., 1917, n.d., 21.
    - Moore, George F., 1910-1929, 22.
    - Sabrice, Wallace C., 1909, 23.
    - Trimble, H., 1949-1952, 24.
    - Wheatland, David P., 1948-1951, 25.
  - B. Charles S. Minot Portrait Correspondence, 1938-1943
    Subseries B includes correspondence from FTL's efforts to raise funds for a memorial portrait of Charles S. Minot at Harvard Medical School.
    Interfiled alphabetically by topic or correspondent. Oversized materials listed in Subseries B are housed in an oversize folder.
    - (Box 1)
    - A-M, 1938, 26-37.
    - Minot Family, 1938-1939, 38.
    - N, 1938, 39-45.
    - Notes, 1938-1939, 46.; (oversized folder)
- II. Teaching Records, 1908-1945
  Series II includes blank tests and course notes from FTL's teaching activities at Harvard Medical School.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - (Box 1)
  - Anatomy, 1921-1942, 47.
  - Dental Students, 1908-1935, n.d., 48.
  - Embryology, 1915-1925, n.d., 49.
  - Exam Notes and Course Comments, 1911-1942, n.d., 50.
  - Gross Anatomy, 1933-1942, 51.
  - Histology, 1924-1940, n.d., 52.
  - Histology and Embryology, 1921-1924, 53.
  - Anatomy and Histology, 1920-1921, 54.
  - Mass. State Board Exam Questions/ National Board Exam Questions, 1919-1938, 55.
  - Microscopic Anatomy, 1926-1945, 56.
  - Neurology, 1924-1925, 1936-1941, 57.
  - Third Year Surgery, 1945, 58.
- III. Administrative Activities Records, 1914-1940
  Series III includes a small amount of notes and correspondence from FTL's work on the Curriculum and Library Committees. Records from the Library Committee document early attempts to merge the Harvard Medical School Library and the Boston Medical Library into one institution.
  Arranged alphabetically by activity.
  - (Box 1)
  - Boston Medical/ Harvard Medical Libraries, 1914-1940, 59-60.
  - Curriculum, 1924, 61.
  - Southard, Elmer, 1915-1916, 62.
- IV. Research Correspondence and Notes, 1663-1951
  Series IV contains correspondence, notes, and photographs from FTL's research activities regarding the history of medicine and microscopes. Includes lecture notes and item captions from his exhibits on medical history and microscopes, as well as 17th and 18th century letters and notes collected for his study and exhibits of the history of medicine
  Photographs listed in Series IV are housed in box 3. Oversized materials listed in Series IV are housed in box 4.
  - A. History of Medicine Research Records, 1663, 1711-1951
    Subseries A contains notes and correspondence from FTL's research activities in the history of medicine.
    Interfiled alphabetically by subject or correspondent. Photographs listed in Subseries A are housed in box 3.
    - (Box 1)
    - Anaesthesia, 1941, n.d., 63.
    - Bacon (Roger) Manuscripts, 1921, 64.
    - Bell, M., n.d., 65.
    - Bischoff, Dr., 1870, n.d., 66.
    - Bowditch, Henry I., n.d., 67.
    - Bowdoin, James, n.d., 68.
    - Broes, Rev. P., 1711, 69.
    - Bromfield, Edward, 1923-1934, n.d., 70.
    - Browncker, William Lord Viscount, 1663., 71.; A.L.s. by William Lord Viscount Browncker [27 October 1663]
    - Browne, Daniel J., 1941, n.d., 72.
    - Burdach, 1837, 73.
    - Coiter, Volcher, 1942-1943, n.d., 74.
    - De Haller, Albertus, n.d., 75.
    - Fleet, John, 1940, 76.
    - Fleet, John, 1940, photograph ((box 3, folder 7))
    - Gesnero, Joh., 1739, 77.
    - Hagenbuch, Johann Kaspar, n.d., 78.
    - Henle, n.d., 79.
    - Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1934-1942, n.d., 80-81.
    - Homaday, W. T., 1879, 82.
    - Homes, Edward, 1816; 1879; 83.
    - Hunley, H., 1854 (?), 1868, 84.; photographic print ((box 3, folder 8))
    - Hyrtl, Joseph, 1925, n.d., 85.
    - James, William, 1941, n.d., 86.
    - Laboratory Motto - Anatomy Department, 1937-1951, 87.; photographic print ((box 3, folder 10))
    - Laterriere, Pierre de Salles, 1940-1945, n.d., 88.
    - Lister, Lord, 1902, n.d., 89.
    - Mather, Cotton, 1934-1942, n.d., 90.
    - Mather, Increase, n.d., 91.
    - Microtomes, 1919-1943, n.d., 92.
    - Muller, Johanne, 1849-1850, 93.
    - Nichols, Francis, 1949-1950, 94.
    - Pompeian Instruments, 1940-1941, 95.
    - Paget, Sir James, 1847-1938, 96.
    - Saltonstall, Sir Richard, 1939, n.d., 97.
    - Schleiden, M .J., 1859, 98.
    - Spurzheim, Gaspard, n.d., 99.
    - Quincy, Dr. H. P. 1939, n.d., 100.
    - Virchon, R., n.d., 101.
    - Warren, John, n.d., 102.
    - Willoughby, Francis, n.d., 103.
    - Winthrop, John, n.d., 104.
    - Wyman, M., 1856, 105.
  - B. Microscope Research Records, 1921-1950
    Subseries B contains records from FTL's research on microscopes. Includes photographs and a catalog of the HMS microscope collection, including a list of microscopes donated by Harold C. Ernst.
    Arranged alphabetically by subject. Photographs listed in Subseries B are housed in box 3. Oversized materials listed in Subseries B are housed in box 4.
    - (Box 1)
    - Allen, 1942-1949, n.d., 106.
    - Bailey, Spencer Tolles, 1939-1950, n.d., 107.; 4 photographs ((box 3, folder 10))
    - Bicknell, 1947, n.d., 108.
    - Electron, 1945-1947, n.d., 109.
    - Ernst Collection, 1921-1947, n.d., 110.
    - Evans, 1939-1950, n.d., 111.
    - Evans, 1939-1950, n.d., photo-reproduction ((box 3, folder 11))
    - Harvard, 1934-1946, n.d., 112.
    - Harvard Books, 1933-1943, 113.
    - History A-L, 1942, n.d., 114.
    - History M-Z, 1942-1944, n.d., 115.
    - Hodges, Stereoscope of Cadaver Dissection, n.d.:, 2 photographs, 2 photographic prints ((box 3, folder 12))
    - (Box 2)
    - Holyoke, 1941-1944, n.d., 1.
    - Jackson, 1947, n.d., 2.
    - Mark Twain, 1939, n.d., 3.
    - Mark Twain, Unidentified Painting, 1939, n.d., photographic print ((box 3, folder 13))
    - Notes from Books and Journals, n.d., 4.
    - Notes from Books and Journals, Dr. Crawford Long, n.d., photographic print ((box 3, folder 14))
    - Pennsylvania, 1946-1950, n.d., 5.; photograph ((box 3, folder 15))
    - Post-Dudley, 1943-1949, n.d.; 6.; photograph ((oversize-box 4, folder 1),, (box 3, folder 16))
    - Wilson, 1934-1950, n.d., 7.; photographic print ((box 3, folder 17))
    - Catalogues 1-167, n.d., 8-11.
  - C. Exhibit Notes, 1932-1940
    Subseries C contains FTL's lecture notes, diagrams, and item captions for medical history and microscope exhibits.
    Arranged alphabetically by topic.
    - (Box 2)
    - Ancients, Introduction of the Microscope, 1932, 12.
    - Aristotle, 1933, 13.
    - Bone-Cartilage, 1933-1934, 14-15.
    - Bone-Smooth Muscle, 1933, 16.
    - Brain, 1933, 17.
    - Cell Theory, 1931-1934, 18-19.
    - Centenary of Schwann, 1938, 20.
    - Circulation, 1931-1936, 21-22.
    - Connective Tissue-Cartilage, 1932, 23.
    - Embryology, 1939, 24.
    - Epithelium - Glands, 1932-1933, 25.
    - Fat and Cartilage, 1934-1935, 26.
    - Galen-Pompeian Instruments, 1940, 27.
    - Glands of Internal Secretion, n.d., 28.
    - Hippocrates, 1933, 29.
    - Hooke, Malpighi, Grew, 1936, 30.
    - Incunabula, 1939, 31.
    - Intestine, 1934-1935, 32.
    - Lymphatics, 1932-1940, 33-36.
    - Microscopes, n.d., 37.
    - Exhibit Labels, unidentified, n.d., 38.
    - Muscle, 1934, 39.
    - (Box 3)
    - Muscle, 1939, 1.
    - Nerves, 1934, 2.
    - Pancreas, 1933, 3.
    - Smooth Muscle, 1936-1937, 4.
    - Spermatazoa, 1933, 5.